Guide to the Mary Ann Phelps Montgomery Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Mary Ann Phelps Montgomery collection
1746-1939
MS 801
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.75
(4 boxes)
A collection of autograph letters and manuscripts, many of leading American public figures, collected by Mary Ann Phelps Montgomery. Fifteen letters are addressed to her father, Governor John Smith Phelps (1814-1866) of Missouri, six were written by James G. Blaine (1830-1893), and five by Thomas C. Reynolds of Missouri. The collection includes items signed by four American presidents, several European heads of state, and prominent members of European nobility.
Montgomery, Mary Ann Phelps, 1847-1943
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mary Ann Phelps Montgomery in 1944.
Scope and Contents
The Mary Ann Phelps Montgomery Collection contains over two hundred letters and autographs of prominent Americans and Europeans spanning the years 1762 to 1937. Mary Ann Phelps Montgomery (1847-1943) was the daughter of Governor John Smith Phelps of Missouri and the wife of James Boyce Montgomery of Portland, Oregon.
Learning of Mrs. Montgomery's autograph collection, Lieutenant Governor Thomas C. Reynolds of Missouri sent her thirty-five letters, which are among the earliest items in the collection. Also included in the collection are fifteen letters (1845-1880) which were written to Mrs. Montgomery's father, Governor Phelps. Mrs. Montgomery continued to expand her autograph collection, adding letters of some American political figures, as well as personal correspondence, through 1937.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by author. Letters by the same person are arranged chronogically within the folder.
Europe; United States -- Politics and government; Autographs; Clement, Pope, XIII, 1693-1769; Frederick, King of Prussia, II, 1712-1786; Joseph Bonaparte, King of Spain, 1768-1844; Maria Theresa, Empress of Austria, 1717-1780; Victoria, Queen of Great Britain, 1819-1901; Blaine, James Gillespie, 1830-1893; Calhoun, John C. (John Caldwell), 1782-1850; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885; Harrison, Benjamin, 1833-1901; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882; Phelps, John S. (John Smith), 1814-1886; Reynolds, Thomas C. (Thomas Caute), 1821-1887; Richelieu, Armand Jean du Plessis, duc de, 1585-1642; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891; Talleyrand-Périgord, Charles Maurice de, prince de Bénévent, 1754-1838; Webster, Daniel, 1782-1852; Wells, Gideon, 1835-1898
- Inventory
  - Airlie, David Stanley William Drummond Ogilvy, 8th earl of, 1880 February 4, September 1, 1881 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Andrews, E. Bay, 1895 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barbour, James, 1838 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Beale, Harriet S. Blaine, 1884 September 30, 1917 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Belmont, August, 1878 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Berclan, Hiram, 1892 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - La Bernadine, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bingham, Henry Harrison, 1885 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Blaine, James Gillespie, 1876 June 6, 1885 May 29-30, 1887 May 21, 1889 October 11, 1890 March 21, 1891 February 8, September 8 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Blaine, Walker, 1889 October 9 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Blodgett, Henry Williams, 1893 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Boardman, Mabel, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bonaparte, Joseph, king of Spain, 1808 November 20 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bryan, William Jennings, 1897 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Buck, Elisha, 1878 November 12 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Buck, Harry A., 1878 June 20 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bunsen, Georg, 1883 December 27, 1886 September 4, 1891 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cabell, Edward Carrington, 1877 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Calhoun, John C., 1841 February 23 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Cannon, Helen A., 1886 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Carlton, Charles Carroll, 1892 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Carnegie, Andrew, 1884 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Carnegie, Louise, 1927 April 13, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Champagny, Jean-Baptiste Nompère de, duc de Cadore, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Chateaubriand, Francoise René, vicomte de, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Chew, Lillian, 1890 March (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Choate, Rufus, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Christie, A., 1917 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Clemens, James, 1845 March 24 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Clemens, James B., 1878 January 13 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Clement XIII (Carolo della Torre di Rezzonico), 1762
    General note
    See: box 4
  - Collins, William Wilkie, 1877 August 16 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Collyer, Robert, 1887 November 14 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Cooke, Jay, 1881 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Collidge, Grace, Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Corbin, Abel Rathbone, 1869 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Couldock, Charles Walter, 1894 May 28 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Cubbas, John, 1887 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Cullough, John M., 1878 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Curtin, Andrew G., 1884 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Curtin, Catherine, 1886 Jan, March 31 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Curtis, E. S., 1906 November 5, 1907 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Custer, Elizabeth B., 1897 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Damas, Ange Hyacinthe Maxence, baron de, Undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Davis, Jefferson, Undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - DeGraw, Peter Voorhes, 1892 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Dessalles, Jean Joseph Paul Augustin, marquis de, Undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Dillon, Sidney, Undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Dodge, Mellisa (Mrs. William E.), 1879 July 19, 1901 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Drayton, William, 1809 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Dromgoole, George C., Undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Duniway, Abigail S., 1883 December 11, 1909 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Dye, Eva Emory, 1924 June 11, 1939 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Elkins, Stephen Benton, 1892 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Eno, William Phelps, 1918 February 21, 1930 February 22 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Fairbanks, Cornelia C., Undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Ferronays, comte de la, Undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Field, Eugene, 1876 February 14 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Fielis, Annie, Undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Florence, William Jarmyn, 1878 November 9, 1882 September 9, 1891 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Folk, Gertrude, Undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Forney, John W., 1878 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Foster, Mary Parks, Undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Francis, D. R., 1903 September 21, 1904 July 16 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Francis, Jane Perry, Undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Frederick II, "The Great," king of Prussia, 1746 March 10, 1766 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Gault, Thomas J., 1880 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Gould, Helen Miller Sheperd, 1902 October 25, November 19 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Grant, Frederick W., 1891 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Grant, Ida Honore, 1891 April 28, June 11, 12, August 25, undated (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Grant, Ulysses S., 1879 November 29 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Greatorex, Eliza, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Greenwood, Albert Burton, 1859 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Grenfell, Wilfred Thomasen, 1931 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Hall, A. Oakey, Undated (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Halpine, Charles Graham, 1867 February (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Hamilton, Frank H., 1881 September 7 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Hamilton, James, 1867 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Harrison, Benjamin, 1891 September 21, 1896 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Harrison, Caroline S., 1892 January (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Harrison, Carrie Icote, 1888 July 3 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Harrison, Mary Scott Dimmick, 1890 January 22, 1900 February 2 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Hauk, Minnie, 1886 September 27, 1893 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Hay, John, Undated (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Henry, Patrick, Undated (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Hill, David J., 1908 November 11 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Hill, Juliet, 1910 November 6, 9 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Holland, Josiah Gilbert, 1867 April 1 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Huss, John, Undated (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Ingersoll, Robert Green, 1884 September 2, 1886 July 2, 1890 September 10 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Irving, Henry, 1884 April 29 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Jackson, Andrew, Undated (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Jacob, [underline], Undated (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Johnstone, Alan, 1892 January 15, 26 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Kane, Thomas S., 1883 September 13 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Keenan, H. F., Undated (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Keith, Jenie A., Undated (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Kidder, Kathryn, 1899 March 18 (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Kipling, Rudyard, 1937 June 3 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Laws, Samuel Spahr, 1880 March 9 (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Lewald, Theodor, Undated (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - Lieber, Francis, Undated (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Limburg-Stirum, Thiery, comte de, 1904 August 2 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Lippe-Weissenfeld, Ferdinand, 1883 December 17, undated (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Logan, Mrs. John A., 1907 December 20 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Longfellow, Henry W., 1864 April 12 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - McBride, George Wickliffe, 1902 February 11 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - McClure, A. K., Undated (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - McCormick, Bessie Chapman, 1922 September 21 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - McGee, Anita Newcomb, 1905 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - McKee, Mary Harrison, 1891 December 17 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - McLean, George Payne, 1901 December 26, 1912 December 5 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - McLoren, bishop, 1894 July 12 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - McPherson, Edla, Undated (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Madison, Dorothy Payne, Undated (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - Maret, Hugues Bernard, duc de Bassano, 1812 January 27 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - Maria Theresia, empress of Austria, 1779 July 21 (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - Marmaduke, John S., 1879 July 15 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Marmont, Auguste Frédéric Louis Viesse de, duc de Raguse, Undated (Box 2, Folder 117)
  - Marshall, Katherine, Undated (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - Martin, C. H., 1930 February 10 (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - Maynell, Wilfred, Undated (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - Miles, Mary S., 1892 Jan, 1901 September 17 (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - Miller, Samuel, 1886 May 19 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - Milton, Hay John, 1864 March 20 (Box 2, Folder 123)
  - Mirabeau, Honoré Gabriel Riquetti, comte de, 1786 April 24 (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - Molé, Louis Matthiew, comte de, 1838 June 10 (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - Moulton, Louise Chandler, Undated (Box 2, Folder 126)
  - Ohlendorff, baron von, 1884 July 7 (Box 2, Folder 127)
  - O'Rell, Max, 1895 February 28 (Box 2, Folder 128)
  - Owen, Ruth Bryan, 1929 April 16 (Box 2, Folder 129)
  - Perry, Edith Weir, Undated (Box 2, Folder 130)
  - Pinchot, Gifford, 1929 December 17 (Box 2, Folder 131)
  - Polk, Trusten, 1870 July 1 (Box 2, Folder 132)
  - Raymond, John T., Undated (Box 2, Folder 133)
  - Read, Thomas Buchanan, 1864 August 12 (Box 2, Folder 134)
  - Reed, Thomas B., 1896 November 25 (Box 2, Folder 135)
  - Reynolds, Thomas C., 1872 February 24, 1877 January 24, 1878 July 25, 1879 January 13, January 28, 1884 August 7, September 9 (Box 2, Folder 136-137)
  - Richardson, Locke, 1890 July 18 (Box 2, Folder 138)
  - Richelieu, Armand Jean du Plessis, cardinal duc de, Undated (Box 2, Folder 139)
  - Rigny, Henri-Daniel, comte de, 1829 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 140)
  - Robertson, William, 1877 April 26 (Box 2, Folder 141)
  - Romero, Matias, 1896 March 10 (Box 2, Folder 142)
  - Roosevelt, Edith K., 1920 September 23 (Box 2, Folder 143)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, Undated (Box 2, Folder 144)
  - Root, Elihu, 1907 December 21 (Box 2, Folder 145)
  - Ryan, H. J., 1877 January 28, October 23, 1892 April 12 (Box 2, Folder 146)
  - St. Albans, William Amelius Aubrey-de-Vere Beauclerk, 10th duke of, 1891 February 5 (Box 2, Folder 147)
  - Saxe, John Godfey, 1855 February 22 (Box 2, Folder 148)
  - Seckendorff, Max, 1892 February 2 (Box 2, Folder 149)
  - Sheridan, Philip Henry, 1856 September 2, November 13 (Box 2, Folder 150)
  - Sherman, Rachel Ewing, Undated (Box 2, Folder 151)
  - Sherman, Thomas Ewing, 1919 July 17 (Box 2, Folder 152)
  - Sherman, William Tecumseh, 1887 June 30, 1890 March 14 (Box 2, Folder 153)
  - Shiras, George, Jr., 1899 March 8 (Box 2, Folder 154)
  - Shiras, Lillian E., 1899 February 27 (Box 2, Folder 155)
  - Sickles, Daniel E., Undated (Box 2, Folder 156)
  - Smith, Charles Emory, 1894 July 16 (Box 2, Folder 157)
  - Sothern, Neo, Undated (Box 2, Folder 158)
  - Spencer, J. C., Undated (Box 2, Folder 159)
  - Stanley-Brown, Mary Garfield, 1893 April 24 (Box 3, Folder 160)
  - Sternberg, Lillian May, Undated (Box 3, Folder 161)
  - Sully, Maximillian, Undated (Box 3, Folder 162)
  - Sumner, Walter Taylor, 1924 December 28 (Box 3, Folder 163)
  - Sumter, Thomas, 1827 September 3 (Box 3, Folder 164)
  - Sunday, William, Undated (Box 3, Folder 165)
  - Talleyrand-Périgord, Charles Maurice de, prince de Bénévent, Undated (Box 3, Folder 166)
  - Tecklenberg, N. Harte van, 1904 September 19 (Box 3, Folder 167)
  - Thackera, Eleanor S., 1908 January 17, 24 (Box 3, Folder 168)
  - Tillard, Henry, 1880 September 2 (Box 3, Folder 169)
  - Townsend, George Albert, 1888 January 6, undated (Box 3, Folder 170)
  - Tower, Charlemagne, 1908 January 18 (Box 3, Folder 171)
  - Usher, J. P., Undated (Box 3, Folder 172)
  - Vanderbilt, William Henry, 1878 October 29 (Box 3, Folder 173)
  - Vedder, Elihu, Undated (Box 3, Folder 174)
  - Versen, Alice von, Undated (Box 3, Folder 175)
  - Versen, Max von, 1892 April 19 (Box 3, Folder 176)
  - Vest, George Graham, 1879 December 11, 1886 January 9, 1901 January 29 (Box 3, Folder 177)
  - Victoria, queen of Great Britain, 1885 October 29
  - Villard, Frances G., 1899 August 23 (Box 3, Folder 178)
  - Villard, Henry, 1900 February 6 (Box 3, Folder 179)
  - Waldersee, Mary Ester Lee, princess von Noer, countess von, 1890 August 14 (Box 3, Folder 180)
  - Walker, Francis A., 1896 May 30, August 8, September 8 (Box 3, Folder 181)
  - Walker, Robert J., Undated (Box 3, Folder 182)
  - Wartegg, Mme de
    See: box 1, folder 77
  - Washburne, Elihu Benjamin, 1878 February 15 (Box 3, Folder 183)
  - Washburne, William Drew, 1892 April 7 (Box 3, Folder 184)
  - Watson, Genevieve, 1904 July 14 (Box 3, Folder 185)
  - Webster, Daniel, Undated (Box 3, Folder 186)
  - Wells, Gideon, 1862 December 18 (Box 3, Folder 187)
  - Wheaton, Henry, Undated (Box 3, Folder 188)
  - Wilson, John M., 1898 July 3 (Box 3, Folder 189)
  - Wolcott, Edward Oliver, 1897 November 15 (Box 3, Folder 190)
  - Zeggio, Jerome, 1905 November 21 (Box 3, Folder 191)
  - Unidentified, Undated (Box 3, Folder 192)
  - Mary Ann Phelps Montgomery's lists of her collection. (Box 3, Folder 193)
  - Folio (Box 4)
    General
    Contains oversize material from Clement XIII (Carolo della Torre di Rezzonico) and Victoria, queen of Great Britain.